Welcome to Essential Hayek
欢迎来到哈耶克简要
I'm Don Boudreaux
我是Don Boudreaux
professor of economics at George Mason University
乔治梅森大学经济学教授
senior fellow with the Fraser Institute
弗雷泽研究所高级研究员
and blogger at Café Hayek
博客Café Hayek的博主之一
This video was part of the Fraser Institute initiative
本视频是由弗雷泽研究所制作的
to present the key ideas of F.A. Hayek in an easily accessible format
对哈耶克关键思想的通俗介绍
In this video, we explore one of Hayek's most profound pursuits
本视频将介绍哈耶克最重要的思想探索之一
which is understanding the difference between legislation and the law
立法和法律的不同
Hayek differentiated between rules consciously designed and imposed on society by government officials
哈耶克区分了两种规则，由政府官员有意设计并施加于社会的、
and rules that emerge undesigned from social interaction among people over time
和无人设计、在人们的互动中自发涌现的
He called rules imposed on society by government officials legislation
他把政府制定的规则称为立法
and he contrast legislation with those rules that emerge, which he called law
把自发涌现的规则称作法律，并把二者进行了对比
Hayek's concept of law is a lot like what we today refer to as social norms
哈耶克所说的法律类似于我们今天所说的社会规范
Let's try to simplify this distinction with an example
让我们举个栗子来说明这种区分
This is Julie
这是Julie
Julie is going to the movies
她正要去看电影
When Julie enters the theater
当Julie来到电影院
she finds a seat and puts a coat on it
她找到了个座位并把外套放了上去
This small act sends a signal to others that the seat is now taken
这个小举动告诉其他人这个位置已经被占了
People recognize from the placing of the coat
人们会从放在那的外套看出
that someone has staked a claim so to speak, on that seat for the duration of the movie
已经有人宣示了这个座位在电影放映期间的使用权
No one will move Julie's coat or sit in that seat
没人会拿开Julie的外套或者去坐那个座位
This rule is a social norm or convention that governs our behavior
这个规则就是一种约束着我们行为的社会规范，或者叫习俗
No government imposed this rule as a law, but so what
没有政府把这条规则写进法典，但那又怎样？
We all recognize and follow this rule
我们都理解并遵守这条规则
and we would interpret someone who ignores this rule by moving Julie's coat
并且假如有人无视这条规则，移走Julie的外套
and taking the seat
一屁股坐下来
as someone who violates the normal social behavior
我们会认为他违反了正常的社会规范
In other words, this social norm constrains the way we act
换句话说，这条社会规范限制了我们的行为可能
and allows us to interact with one another more effectively
并且让我们能更有效地与他人互动
Another example can be seen when Julie goes to get popcorn
当Julie去买爆米花时，我们可以看到另一个例子
There is a line at the concession stand
人们正在小卖部排队购物
but rather than push to the front of line by cutting ahead of everyone
不过Julie并没有直接插队到第一个
Julie stands at the back and waits for turn
而是排在了队伍最后耐心等待
This is a typical social norm that we all naturally follow without thinking
这是一个我们所有人都无需思考就会自然遵守的社会规范
and we expect others to do the same
并且我们预期别人也会这么做
It doesn't require government for its enforcement
它也无需政府来保障它的执行
Hayek explained how the social norms that emerge over time
哈耶克解释了此类
through people interacting with one another and figuring out what works
通过人们的互动和试错自发产生的社会规范
powerfully govern our behaviors toward others
是如何有力地约束我们对其他人的行为的
so that society functions productively, collaboratively, and peacefully
从而让社会和平、有效率、又相互合作
To learn more and download  for free
想要下载和更多了解《哈耶克简要》
visit www.essentialhayek.org
请访问www.essentialhayek.org
翻译 by tcya